Let's recap what we've talked about the
last couple lectures to lead into today.
Uh so for policy gradients uh we started
with our first reinforcement learning
algorithm where our goal was to run a
policy to collect a batch of data and
improve the policy using that batch of
data and then repeat this process so
that your approach can get better and
better with experience.
Um and the way that we actually improve
the policy using this data uh is this
equation that we've looked at where uh
we collect samples from the policy. We
then um try to increase the probability
for actions in the data that have a high
reward in the future. And then we found
that if we subtracted a baseline that's
the average reward that encourages us to
have the policy do more of the above
average things and less of the below
average things. Um and we also talked
about a way um right now everything here
requires that the data be sampled from
the exact policy that you're going to be
taking a gradient step on. And we talked
about how we can use importance weights,
this term right here, uh to in order to
do multiple gradient steps so that um so
that we don't have to be collect a new
batch of data every single time we want
to take one gradient step.
Uh we also talked about value functions
uh and we talked about how a value uh
for a policy of a state is the future
expected rewards starting at state s and
following pi thereafter.
And we talked about a Q function which
is very similar to a value function um
except instead of starting at state S,
you're going to start at state S and
then take take action A and then follow
the policy.
Uh and we can um kind of think about
these as follows. So if we have a given
state that we want to estimate the value
of for a policy, then we can run that
policy and the value is capturing the
expected sum of rewards. So basically uh
the sum of rewards of each of these
trajectories averaged over these
trajectories um for that state and that
policy. Uh and and we can write this as
the summation over future time steps of
our reward if we're starting at ST and
following our policy pi.
And then for the Q function um instead
of starting at S and running the policy
we'll start at S take A and then run the
policy. Uh and so we will then be
averaging over uh the trajectories that
averaging this the sum of rewards over
the trajectories that uh were kind of a
result of running the policy after
taking action A at state S. Um we can
write this as this again the sum over
the future of the future rewards
conditioning on starting in state us
taking action a and then running up the
policy in the future.
Um great then we also talked about the
advantage function and this is
essentially how much better is it to
take one action then to follow the
policy and we can think of this as the Q
function for that state and action minus
the value function at that state. And
this is these are all for a particular
policy pi.
Um now to think a little bit more about
kind of intuitively what value functions
and Q functions mean um we can take a
look at just one quick example. Uh so I
think I mentioned in lecture one this
example of how um DeepMind developed an
AI system that could uh outperform and
and beat the kind of the champion at Go.
Uh and the system was called Alph Go.
And they used reinforcement learning to
do this. And if you were to think about
um this example, say the reward is the
outcome of the game. So it's uh whether
or not Alph Go won or lost.
And then the value function you can
think of as the expected outcome given
the state of the board and the policy
that's being run. And so if you have a
better policy, the value function is
going to be higher. And likewise, if
you're in a board state where things are
looking good for that policy, then
you're also going to have a higher value
function. And so the value function is
influenced both by the policy and by the
state. Uh and yeah, um so that's kind of
an example of of what a value function
looks like. And likewise, um a Q
function would be similar except instead
of running the policy from the state,
you'd be considering a particular action
first before running the policy.
Okay. Um so we talked about actor critic
methods uh on Friday last week and we um
we introduced this this form this
equation which looks a lot like policy
gradients um where we're summing over
examples um except now instead of using
the sum of rewards uh in a given
trajectory we're using our estimate of
how good an action is or the advantage
and this comes from uh the the sum of
awards which is the Q function minus the
average sum of awards which is the
value. Uh, and you can think of this as
being different from policy gradient and
that we're estimating which actions are
good and bad and then encouraging the
policy to do more of the stuff that we
think is good.
Um, and then we talked about how do we
actually estimate this like what's good
and bad. Um this is referred to as
policy evaluation. And we can fit a
value function a neural network that
takes his input the state and outputs a
scalar value. And um where and we fit
this as uh trying to predict the uh
either just the sum of rewards or the
next reward plus the value function
where we're bootstrapping off of our own
estimates or the sum of a short set of
uh a short trajectory of rewards plus
the value function after that.
Um and then this advantage function is
equal to the reward plus the next value
function minus the current value
function.
>> Okay. Um so let's get into uh the main
topic of today which is that we talked
about actor critic methods last week.
We're primarily considering on policy
actor credit methods and today we're
going to uh get into uh two like real
algorithms that people use uh PO and
SACE and we will start from the actor
credit formulation and see how we can
make them off policy to be more
efficient uh and then we'll at the end
we'll talk about how uh PO SACE and
imitation learning compare to each other
um and yeah so the key learning goals is
like really the key concepts behind
practical algorithms like PO and SACE.
Okay, so um we have our actor critic
method. Um this is these are the steps
that we go through for an on policy
actor method where we sample data fit
rewards with our value function. Then we
estimate the advantage with this
equation here for all of our uh states
and actions in our buffer or um in this
set of data. Uh then we estimate what
the gradient of our policy is and update
our gradient.
Um now if we want to be able to take
multiple gradient steps, we need to be
able to evaluate our gradient not just
at our um at the current policy that
collected the data, but um after we've
taken a gradient step, uh for example,
after after we take step five, we're now
going to have a new set of parameters
that were different from what was
collected the data in step one.
And so um what we're going to do is
we're going to use importance weights
which we saw in the policy gradient
lecture. And so our new objective is
going to or our new gradient um is going
to look a little bit different. Uh so
say that we collected data with pi
theta. Now we've taken a gradient step
and we have pi theta prime. So we want
to be able to evaluate the gradient of
the objective at theta prime.
And to do this, we will reuse the data
that we collected from pi theta in step
one. And we're then going to use the
same gradient step as before, but we're
going to weight the gradient term uh
with an importance ratio that is uh a
ratio between our new policy pi theta
prime and the policy that was used to
collect the data which is pi theta.
Um so we have this is our importance
weight term right here and the rest will
look the same as before um where we'll
be evaluating
uh the
uh the gradient of log pi times the
advantage our advantage estimate this
advantage estimate will still be for our
the policy before taking a gradient step
uh pi theta and this will be uh for a
given
S and A pair
uh for for the the SA pair here.
Okay. So this is our new gradient.
Um so that's here. Now
in principle once we've done this this
means that we can take multiple gradient
steps. So we can sample a batch of data
once and then
uh fit our our advantage estimates and
then compute our gradient, take a
gradient step and then recomputee our
gradient, take a gradient step and so
forth. And the only thing that's going
to change as we take more gradient steps
is this importance weight here. And of
course we'll be be doing back
propagation on our new parameters rather
than our old parameters. and our
advantage estimates will still be based
off of the old policy. Now, there's
something that can go wrong here.
Um, and to see what can go wrong, it's
helpful to actually look at the
surrogate objective. Right now, we're
looking at the gradient that we're going
to be applying. Um but when we actually
implement this in practice we'll be
having some surrogate objective that we
uh that we construct in order to use
auto differentiation to get the
gradients for free from PyTorch. Uh and
so if we were to write down the
surrogate objective for this uh we need
to formulate some objective such that
the gradient of our surrogate objective
is equal to this right here.
Now to do that we can remember that we
have this kind of convenient identity
where um where a probability times the
grad log of a probability is equal to
the the gradient of the original
probability. This is kind of the same uh
kind of log trick that we've been seeing
uh we use to formulate the original
policy gradient objective.
And the way this comes in handy is that
we actually see this like pi grad log pi
right here. And so this means that this
is equal to the gradient of pi theta
prime. And if we want to then construct
a surrogate objective such that its
gradient is this, then
this surrogate objective is simply
going to be uh we can replace this with
pi theta of a given s. And then we'll
still have the other terms uh pi theta
and the advantage
right here.
this is these well let's just say this
is just over I all the examples uh in
our batch
and so the way that I formulated this is
the surrogate objective is the gradient
of this sur objective is equal to this
right here um and we see that by if we
take the gradient of this with respect
to theta prime we get grad theta prime
right here and the gradient of uh theta
prime of pi is equal to p theta prime *
grad log pi theta prime.
So you can see this on the slides. Um so
here's our surrogate objective right
here.
Now if we look at the surrogate
objective um so the policy is going to
be trying to maximize this uh when we
take gradient steps on our policy.
And
if we look at this um if we're trying to
maximize this objective,
we have our advantage estimates. And so
that the thing that the policy will want
to do is it will probably want to take
the advantage estimates that are
positive and increase the probability of
our actions for those. Um and especially
if there were actions that had very low
probability that we'd want to increase
this a lot so that we can get a very
high ratio here. um such that we kind of
increase the likelihood of actions for
high advantages and then for negative
advantages we'll want to decrease the
probability. Now this all seems
reasonable here. Um the thing that's a
little bit tricky is that these
advantages are still based off of the
old policy um and they were estimated
based on uh kind of a single batch of
data.
And so if you take too many gradient
steps on the surrogate objective, it
means that uh you might actually kind of
in some ways overfitit. You might be
using uh these advantages at some point
when they might become out of date and
may no longer be applicable to your new
policy.
And so the basically the the challenge
that can come up is you might get really
unstable learning.
As a rough visual for what this might
look like is um if you were to plot the
let's say this is the number um the
number of uh examples of like state
actions that you've collected
and then the y-axis is like the the
rewards that your policy is seeing over
the course of learning like as it
collects more data. Um if you take only
one gradient step for every batch of
data that you collect then your learning
will be uh might look something like
this where it learns very slowly because
you can only take one gradient step for
each batch of data and that means that
um it's going to take many many data
points in order to learn. Um so this is
for one gradient step.
Now say you maybe increase this a little
bit. So you take like five gradient
steps um then you should learn a little
bit faster. So maybe you'll learn
something like this.
Uh because you're taking more gradient
steps per data point. And so with
respect to the amount of data that
you're collecting, your reward should
increase more.
Uh but then if you try to get a little
bit greedy and do um do a lot more
gradient steps on this objective, you
might start to overfitit your advantages
and you'll get something where uh maybe
you'll actually like kind of start to
increase reward very quickly. Uh but
then uh like learning might be unstable
and at some point it might even uh
collapse because your policy um will
overfitit those advantages. they'll get
some kind of really bad policy or a
policy that is like like increased the
probability to one for some advantage um
but done so in a way that makes the
policy performance poor and so this
would be uh like I don't know how
exactly how many gradient step this
would be but this would be uh kind of
more gradient steps than uh than the
others and this would be too many
gradient steps essentially so the
question is what does the behavior of an
overfit policy look like in practice um
the
as anam like it really depends on the
the problem. uh as as one example, it
might if it's overfitting quite a bit,
it might be assigning try to be
assigning like a very very high
probability to like one particular
action that um has a high advantage in
the data. And when it does that, it
might actually also like increase the
probability of um of other actions
around it just because like neural
networks are somewhat smooth. And when
you do that, it might um it might be a
very deterministic policy that no longer
explores. And also it might kind of like
um
I well maybe as like a
it's a little bit hard to to I don't
know exactly what would happen. Um but
the if you had like a 2D agent that's
like moving around in a grid um and
maybe you're like your goal is to get
here then a good policy would like um
would go here. and a policy that's
overfit, I would expect to potentially
like um maybe maybe for example, it
learns that like going right is good,
but doesn't figure out that like you
need a stop here um and doesn't figure
out that you need to like go up. Then
what the overfitit policy might do is it
might like take a straight line here and
then like keep on trying to go like
roughly in this direction and then end
up in the corner. Um because it's kind
of overfit to uh one batch of data that
told it to go this way but didn't figure
out that it needs the thumb. Yeah,
exactly. So this is five gradient steps
on um kind of five loops of this before
you then collect a new batch of data um
and then refit your your value function.
Currently it is um it's refit only on
the current batch of data. Um later this
lecture we'll see uh how we can
potentially reuse previous batches. Um
so the question is what is the
importance of using the surrogate
objective versus the original
formulation? Um this is the same
formulation. Uh the I found it helpful.
I think it's a little bit more intuitive
if you look at the surrogate objective
to understand that it's like these
importance weights are really trying to
like make it like it's very easy to
increase the probability. Um you can
also see that with the gradient as well
where it's going to be like trying to
increase the probability. Um but I think
it's just a little bit easier to see
with the surrogate objective. Um we'll
also in a minute see how we can change
the surrogate objective and it gets a
little bit more complicated. um like PO
looks a little bit more compulated if
you look at the gradient versus if you
look at the surrogate objective. Yeah.
So the question is why are we using the
importance weights to evaluate the
gradient? Um so this importance weight
term is is what is allowing us um to to
do more than one gradient step in the
first place. And if you um it's kind of
what it's what's allowing this kind of
blue curve to do kind of better in some
ways. If you don't have the importance
weights, then it's essentially um uh
it's yeah the it's not allowing you to
actually accurately uh estimate the
gradient on um on the old batch of data.
>> Yeah. So what happens when the a network
is too old? So um if the advantages uh
the advantage estimates are going to be
based off of like um some batch of data,
it's not like infinite. uh it's going to
be uh a batch of data that might be I
don't know around like um a few thousand
time steps of data and those advantage
estimates will be they're also kind of
under the old policy before we took any
gradient steps and so if you take a lot
of gradient steps on this objective
those advantages are not like um they're
only true for the old policy um and they
were also only based off of um a limited
batch of data and primarily because they
were based off of the old policy uh the
when you're actually after you've taken
like I don't know 50 gradient steps or
100 gradient steps uh they become out of
date and the policy um like for example
maybe your old policy
uh in this example it's possible that
your old policy um right here like maybe
it did actually decide to like go up for
example um so then you learn that like
if you're over here you should like go
this way because later you will go up um
because your that's what your advantages
are telling you uh but then in practice
this once you have your new policy uh in
the future you'll be doing something
different and so those advantages over
here are no longer like accurate no
longer valid and you need to collect a
new batch of data under your new policy
in order to have accurate advantages.
Okay. So
um the policy is going to increase
probability on actions with high
advantages. These advantages are based
on the old policy and so they'll get out
of date and so if you take a lot of
gradient steps the policy is really in
it's I guess the other thing that I
didn't mention is that when it's
increasing the probability it's also
inherently like trying to differ
significantly from the old policy like
it's not only encouraged to increase
probability on advantages but that is
going to cause it to change very
different change drastically from the
old policy. Um, and this means that
you're also like because you're also
changing a lot, these advantages are
even less likely to be uh to be up to
date with your current policy.
Um, and so there's a question of like
how do we address this? And there's
actually a couple things that we can do
in order to actually be able to stably
take more gradient steps. Um and the key
idea is if we keep the pol the new
policy to be a little bit more close to
the original policy then those advantage
estimates are more likely to be valid.
And there's two ways in which we might
be able to encourage the the um the new
policy to be similar to the old one. One
would be to add a term to our surrogate
objective that explicitly is going to
try to encourage the policies to be
similar. And these policies are
representing distributions over actions.
And so one way that we could do that is
to um add a term to our objective. So
we'll have like um we have J
uh we have our surrogate objective right
here. Um if we have it be equal to uh
the same thing as what's written up
there. Uh maybe I'll call this like some
um let's call this uh I don't know uh
co for constraint. This is going to be
equal to the original surrogate
objective that we're trying to maximize.
And then we can add a penalty that
discourages you from changing too much
from the previous policy. And that
penalty could take the form of
uh the kale divergence between two
distributions.
So this could be the kale divergence
between the new policy distribution
and the old policy distribution.
And so if we add this to our surrogate
objective, what this will do is it will
encourage it um it'll encourage the
policies to stay close to one another um
while you take more gradient steps and
so your advantage functions will be more
accurate. Um and this will allow you to
more stably take more gradient steps. Um
now it will still be constraining your
step size and so it's like you need it's
a little bit of a balance. Um, but
essentially the result of something like
this in principle should look I'm out of
colors. Uh, maybe should look um kind of
something like this if you add uh if you
do more gradient steps but with this
kale penalty. So the comment was um the
it's it's trying it's incentivizing
because of this ratio right here and um
it can make this um it's it's
controlling the upper part. The lower
part is fixed. This is the old policy.
Um it's controlling this new one and and
so uh it can make this like very large
or very small. Uh and that will cause
these weights to like either go to zero
or become uh or or if I'm or potentially
be infinite depending on how small the
old policy probability was. Um and the
uh and when we constrain um how
different these are then uh we're
encouraging this to be closer to one. Um
so you can't just like like uh push this
to like infinity or you can't just push
it to zero. Yeah. So a couple comments
um were here. So the first was that uh
to do this kale constraint we actually
need to keep around our old parameters
in memory. Um, this can actually be kind
of annoying uh to do. Uh, it increases
your memory costs and this is actually
not uncommon to do with large language
models and you'll have to keep around
the full set of weights for your old
language model um in order to do this.
That said, there are ways to potentially
cache this. So, if you you potentially
could um uh just keep around the
probabilities that were assigned uh to
different different states um for a
given batch of data. Uh and then the
second note was that for this surrogate
objective uh this ratio is initially
going to be one um for because uh uh
yeah and then once you take one gradient
step that's where this starts to uh
potentially diverge. Yeah. The goal is
to basically constrain how far how much
you're changing the policy and only to
change the policy um a little bit uh
rather than like a ton. Yeah. Um, one
other example to one other way to think
about this is like if your policy is a
neural network that's taking as input
like images for example um you're need
you need a lot of uh gradient steps in
order to change the features of those
images. Uh and so you you want to be
able to take a lot of gradient steps uh
but without substantially changing the
action distribution that the policy is
going to take so that you can still
refine your features um without like
causing this objective to uh overfitit
too much. Yeah. Yeah. So the question
was how do we um how do we encourage it
to change a little bit but not too much.
Um often times you'll have some
hyperparameter that is in front of this
kale divergence um that needs to be
tuned. Uh and so and so this beta is
like a hyperparameter um and this will
control how much you're allowing it to
shift. uh the this ends up being often
times a fairly important hyperparameter
when you use kale constraints. Uh at the
same time uh I don't you don't need to
tune it like usually people tune it like
uh within an order of magnitude rather
than like very carefully finding like
423 whatever. Yeah. So the question was
how does this look like for the kind of
original gradient um and not quite
understanding the surrogate. So um the
circuit objective is kind of what we're
plugging into PyTorch uh in order and
then then PyTorch um or TensorFlow or
Jax will then compute the gradients for
us. Uh and the when they compute the
gradients for us they will get the first
line. Um and so these are
uh the gradient of the second line is
equal to the the first line.
Um and then for this um you can then
plug you can uh if you were to implement
this you have your original surrogate
objective and then you just plug in this
ter this term as well you can um look up
the expression for kale divergence
between like two categorical
distributions or two gausian which in
the gausian case it will be a function
of the means and variances and um then
just add that to your surrogate
objective and then have pietorch um give
you the gradients. You could also um if
you write down the equation for a
particular distribution, you could also
write get the gradients yourself if you
want to take a look at that. What's the
difference between J theta and J tilda
theta? So um the
I'm using J tilda to refer to the
surrogate objective um because it's
technically not the true objective. The
original J theta objective uh was equal
to like the expected sum of rewards. Um
so it was like the sum of rewards here.
Yeah.
Yeah. So J this is an estimation of
that. Yeah.
Okay. So the first idea is use a kale
constraint. Um this is actually very
common to do. Uh we will leave it at
this for now. We actually won't use KL
constraints. Um there is actually a
version of PO that uses KL constraints.
Uh but it's not the most common version
but it's also used a lot in um in
preference optimization. So we'll
probably see it again in a couple weeks.
Um and then there's actually a second
idea. So we could add this kind of
constraint in the objective. The other
thing that we could do is we could um
for this this ratio right here. Uh we
could simply remove the incentive for
the policy to change this ratio a lot.
And the way that we would do that is we
could actually just clip this ratio so
that the ratio never exceeds some value
and never goes below some value. Uh and
so what that would look like is
um h this is like I guess this is
version one. Uh
what version two would look like
is
we would be taking these importance
weights and we would be
clipping them. So we have the importance
weights pi theta prime / pi theta
and we would be clipping these to be uh
between some lower value 1 - epsilon and
some higher value 1 plus epsilon.
epsilon could be something like 2. So,
you're saying that if it goes below uh8
then it'll just be 08. And if this goes
above 1.2, we're just going to leave it
as 1.2.
Um, now this clipping, this is a little
bit informal. Uh if I were to write this
out mathematically what this would look
like um let's say that let's call this w
this weight right here then if we wanted
to clip it below by 1 minus epsilon then
we would be uh taking the max between w
and 1 - epsilon. And if we wanted to
then clip this above by 1 plus epsilon,
then we'd be taking the min between this
and 1 + epsilon.
And now
if we use this clipped importance
weights in our objective right here,
then once the policy changes the ratio
to be like above 1.2, two, it's no
longer going to be able like increasing
the probability any further isn't going
to help it. It's no longer going to be
incentivized to increase the probability
further because the objective will just
stay as 1.2 times the advantage. And so
it isn't actually explicitly
constraining the policy not to change,
but it's removing the incentive to
change significantly from the old
policy. Yes. So it cannot be below 1
minus epsilon and it cannot be above 1
plus epsilon. um a value of epsilon
that's like used in practice is
something like um it might be like
something like 0.2. Uh so it's not tiny.
Um sometimes you refer to epsilon as
tiny numbers. Uh in this case it's it's
going to be constraining it to be like
between 0.8 and 1.2.
Okay. So this sort of idea of bounding
the importance weights um is actually a
key one of the key ideas behind uh PO
which is a popular RL algorithm.
And
so let's see um if we were to then put
this clipping into practice, we could
take our surrogate objective and then
replace the importance weights by the
clipped importance weights right here uh
in order to get a modified surrogate
objective.
Now, um there's a couple more tricks
that PO introduces
uh to try to get stable reinforcement
learning improvement.
Um
so in this first trick is no longer
incentivized to deviate significantly.
Now, um,
one thing that's a little bit funky
about these importance weights is that,
um, it there is actually a possibility
that the, um, that it might actually,
uh, the clipping in some rare cases
might actually make the objective
better. Um if for example the policy
ended up assigning a very um a very low
probability to um like a negative
advantage and it went below the
advantages then you're clipping it to a
higher weight. Um and so
um one thing that PO does is and the
kind of the final objective of PO is to
take this clipped objective uh but take
the minimum with respect to the original
objective and this minimum is just um
making sure that the clipping will never
make the objective better and it
formulates uh a lower bound. It ensures
that this is a lower bound on the
original uh surrogate objective.
Um, and this means that we're going to
be maximizing a lower bound on our
objective. And usually u if you're ever
going to be like um it's if you're ever
going to be optimizing or maximizing
something that's different from your
original objective, it's good if it's a
lower bound because it means that you're
actually going going to be um you're not
going to be like maximizing something
that you can maximize beyond the
original objective.
Um cool. So this is the final PO
surrogate objective. The motivation
behind trick one or trick two. Trick
two. Um so the motivation behind trick
two. Um
I don't I'm not actually sure how often
this happens in practice like how
critical this is. But the the motivation
is that if you are in a scenario you
might actually be in a scenario where um
maybe it it it like increased the the
probability on a lot of the good stuff.
It decreased the probability on a lot of
the bad stuff. But in some um some of
the rare circumstances where like maybe
increasing the probability on a good
stuff let it there was another advantage
that had a similar state that was
actually really bad. Um and maybe
increase the probability on both of
those. Uh in that case the clipping
clipping it at 1.2 for that second one
is actually making it better is actually
like making the objective better. Uh
because you're then saying okay maybe it
assigned a really high probability to
this bad action. We're then going to
clip that at 1.2 2 or something like
that. Um and so if we take the minimum
with respect to the original objective
[clears throat] is at the state action
level at the data point level uh this is
going to ensure that um those situations
aren't happening. Uh and so I guess
explicitly say you have um
say you have
uh
a particular state and action pair where
the advantage is like I don't know
negative a thousand or something like
that. So something really large then uh
and say that your your new um
your new policy for this state and
action uh decided to give it like a
probability of like 0.9 or something
very high. Uh and the original policy
maybe gave it a probability of Whoops.
If the original policy gave it a
probability of like 0.1
uh then in this case the ratio between
these two is 9. Uh and then when we clip
it, it then would be clipped to 1.2.
Uh and then that's actually once we clip
it to 1.2, we'll multiply 1.2 bygative
a,000. And so that's actually going to
be making the objective better than if
we hadn't clipped the objective. And so
what this trick number two does is it
means that um it actually doesn't get to
do the clipping for this particular data
point. Uh and and this will
disincentivize it from um from making
these kinds of accidents which is a good
thing to do. Um so you're asking why
don't we just clip above and not clip
below. So there is actually an analogous
version of this. Um if you just make
this negative and flip these uh where
the clipping could also make it um make
the objective better. Uh like for
example if a hat is uh for a given state
and action pair is positive 1,00 and the
new policy assigns 0.1 and the old
policy assigns
um 0.9.
Then now if you did this um by accident
then the uh or if it happened to do this
as um as part of the when optimizing
other data points then now the ratio is
going to be uh 1 over9 which is very
small. You multiply that by a th00and um
if you clip the one over n by 0.8 uh
that's actually be making the objective
better. Um and so generally clipping on
both sides and then taking the lower
bound um is uh prevents like both of
these kinds of scenarios uh from being
encouraged through clipping.
Okay. Um so this is the final PO
surrogate objective. Uh the last thing
uh the last trick that PO does is on
estimating the advantage.
Uh so
to estimate the advantage um there's a
third trick that's used. This is
actually a trick where I'm not um I'm
not sure how necessary it is myself. Uh
I haven't done a ton of comparisons. Uh
the and the way that it works is you um
you still could be fitting a value
function vi in the normal way um either
with Monte Carlo or bootstrapping. Uh
but then once you fit that value
function uh previously the equation for
our value function was the reward plus
the next value minus the current value
and
instead of just using kind of a horizon
of one uh it's actually going to use a
varying horizon. So um you can think of
before we were estimating the advantage
of a given state and action. We were
using the reward
at that state plus uh the value at the
next state minus the value at the
current state. These were all for pi. Um
and then we're
had hats on each of these. Uh but you
can also estimate the advantage um using
something that kind of looks like
endstep uh returns where you're actually
going to be summing over multiple reward
functions uh multiple of the rewards
into the future um and subtracting that
future reward uh or adding that future
value um instead of adding just one step
into the future. Uh you can sort of
think of this as like um we were talking
about bias and variance before. Uh if
you use if you calculate these different
advantages with varying horizons um and
then weight them accordingly then you
can get um advantage estimates that uh
that have kind of varying uh varying
variance and maybe have uh less bias
than the if you just use the onestep
estimate right here.
I think that there's some argument in
terms of bias and variance that can be
made. Uh but the um it's also like not
100% clear if it's necessary in my
opinion. Right. Yeah. So there's now
going to be a hyperparameter here with
regard to how do you choose these
weights with regard to the different um
the different endstep returns. The um
uh generally you'll uh mostly use the
earlier ones uh so that you have less
variance. uh and usually you will choose
it to kind of decay very quickly as the
horizon increases. So you're mostly
still going to be using uh the like t
equals 1 or n equals 1, right? So if
you're using these weights, do you set
gamma to one or do you use them
together? Uh you'll actually you'll use
them together uh and the um and you'll
get if you write this out, you'll get a
term that like multiplies gamma and
lambda here. Um so the question was is
this the same as like taking a weighted
average of different endstep returns uh
for different ends. So the one thing
that's different is we're still going to
be fitting the value function um in the
normal way and then this is this is in
terms of how we estimate the advantage
but otherwise it's um is very kind of
you can think of it as endstep returns
but averaging the different uh the
different ends um in order to get an
estimate. Uh what's the benefit of using
GA? I think it like I'm not
I think it's a little bit hard to to
motivate. I think one way to view it is
that if you just use this onestep return
um especially if the the time steps are
very close together then um this might
be um if this estimate is like a if your
V's are not completely accurate then
this estimate might be a bit off and if
you increase this horizon then um you'll
get potentially a better estimate. Now,
why not just use like one value of n
versus a mixture? Um, perhaps it helps
you hedge a little bit if you're not
sure which value of n is correct. Uh,
but I don't have like a a great
motivation myself for it. And I'm
actually not if you use it and don't use
it, I'm not 100% sure what the
performance is is like.
Okay. Um, cool. So the final PO
algorithm, we sample a batch of data. We
fit a value function to that data and
then we evaluate this um generalized
advantage estimate that we just talked
about and then we will update the policy
by taking m gradient steps on your
surrogate objective where the surrogate
objective uses these clipped importance
weights uh using the the GA estimate of
the advantage function.
uh and then you can repeat this process
after taking m gradient steps then kind
of sample a new batch of data fit a new
value function to that and repeat the
process.
Um in order to get like a rough sense
for like what this looks like here are
some example hyperparameters. Now
generally hyperparameters are something
that you would tune per domain. So this
is not like my recommended
hyperparameter necessarily, but just to
give a rough sense for what this looks
like. Um the batch of data might have
around 2,000 time steps in it. So if you
have um like a long horizon problem that
has like a thousand time steps, this
might actually be only a couple
trajectories. If you have a shorter
horizon problem, this might be uh more
trajectories.
uh when you update the policy on step
four, uh the a common hyperparameter is
something around 10 epochs on the data
set that was collected in step one. And
so this would be if your batch size is
64, um this might be around 300 gradient
steps. Uh and so this means that in
comparison uh to before we're actually
because we introduced this clipping
we're actually able to take uh 300
gradient steps without um having really
unstable improvement. So that's good.
Uh clipping range I mentioned like 0.2
is something that that might be
reasonable. Um, and then you might run
this uh around like 500 times uh this
this full outer loop 500 times um in
order to get around a million total time
steps of experience.
uh if you run this algorithm if you run
PO we'll see some other examples
actually some cooler examples at the end
of the lecture but if you run PO on uh
this very simple uh simulated half
cheetah um like the right half of a
cheetah or something uh then and you
look at as you collect more time steps
of data what does the reward look like
uh there are a number of algorithms here
uh this beige one is vanilla policy
gradient it's a slightly smarter version
of vanilla policy gradient but is
basically vanilla policy gradient where
you're not fitting the advantage
function and you're not doing the
clipping and then PO is up here and you
can see that it's able to with less
experience able to improve much faster
because it's doing um because it's
fitting the advantage function and
because it's doing uh the clipping on
the gradient in order to take many more
gradient steps um on uh on a single data
point. Yeah. So can I explain the the
arrow from four to one and how are the
parameters being updated? So um this
arrow is just saying that after we
finish step four then we're going to go
back to step one and collect a new batch
of data. When we do that we're not going
to uh we're not we're going to kind of
keep our policy um as it was at the
current time step um and then and yeah
keep on iterating. And so at this point
actually theta will become the previous
theta prime um and you'll be sampling a
batch of data from um your latest
policy.
And then the other thing here is that um
for this value function uh you could
warm start it at the previous value
function or you could train it from
scratch. Uh depends a little bit on the
domain. So in terms of these plots the
question is do you um fit the best set
of hyperparameters and then run it?
Yeah. So each of them will have its own
set of hyperparameters and the best
practice is to uh figure out good
hyperparameters on like one environment
or maybe two environments and then apply
those hyperparameters to the remaining
environments in your experiments. Um
there are scenarios where you might need
a new set of hyperparameters for a
different domain. For example, if you
are controlling something at like one
hertz versus 50 hertz um or optimizing a
language model versus a half cheetah um
the hyperparameters will be different.
Uh so uh there is some variability
there.
Um it is like one good practice is to
not tune your hyperparameters per
environment because then you're
essentially using more like more data
more samples um in order to get those
hyperparameters in the first place and
that wouldn't be reflected on this curve
right here.
Okay. Um we should move on um but happy
to answer it after after class. Uh so so
far we've talked about um using one
batch of data uh for one gradient step.
That's the fully on policy version and
we've looked at using one batch of
policy data for multiple gradient steps
and this is off policy. Uh what I'd like
to talk about for the rest of the
lecture is can we be even more off
policy. Uh so can we reuse previous
batches of data rather than recollecting
a new batch each time like all of the
past trial and error experience.
And there's two ideas for doing this.
One is that we actually need to retain
all of our past data. uh we'll call uh
we'll use a term called a replay buffer
that you actually saw in homework one
where we will have a data set of past
past data we'll keep on adding to it and
at some point we might also uh remove
some like very old data from it uh we
this called a replay buffer because
you're sort of replaying your past
experiences
and then the second idea is we actually
need to adjust some of the equations to
remove some of the on policy assumptions
in order to be able to actually use all
of our past data
Okay, so what this looks like is we'll
take our actor critic algorithm. Um, but
to make it off policy, we'll we can
think of it as getting one time step of
data, then updating our policy, getting
another time step, updating our policy,
and so forth. So rather than getting one
batch and then doing updates, we'll be
we can actually do this much more
online.
Um, and when we update our policy, this
will actually be coming from a replay
buffer. uh we'll be actually doing
gradient steps using um our p all of our
past experiences rather than just our
immediate past experience.
Um and so
in particular when we collect experience
we'll want to then add this to our
replay buffer and when we then update
our policy we want to use a mini batch
sampled from all previous data rather
than just our last batch of data. So
that's kind of like the modifications we
need to make in order to use a replay
buffer.
So walking through this uh we start with
an empty replay buffer. We then collect
experience from our policy. We add that
to the replay buffer and then we sample
a batch um a a transition state, action,
reward, and next state from the replay
buffer. This this there's a small
probability this could be exactly what
we just sampled. um but otherwise it'll
be something randomly sampled from our
previous experience.
Then we'll update our value function
using uh the batch of data that we just
sampled from the buffer.
Uh we can update our value function with
the same uh with the same objective
before, but now we're going to be
averaging over our mini batch.
Um and then we can evaluate the
advantage and then take a gradient step
on our policy.
Um so that's kind of the mechanics of
replay buffers.
Uh now and
uh yeah finally update the policy and
then kind of repeat this process. Um
unfortunately this algorithm right now
is currently broken.
Uh and it's broken in two different
ways. Uh the first way that it's broken
is right here. So
um say that we're using bootstrapping to
update our value function. uh then our
target would be the reward at the
current time step plus the our value
estimate uh for the next state
and so I have a question for you and the
question is when we're fitting a value
function on all of the data in the
replay buffer so this is the data from
all of our previous policies um the
question is what policy are we learning
a value function for when we uh fit the
value function this way uh from data in
our replay buffer and so I'll give you
kind of two minutes to discuss that and
then we'll come back.
Okay, let's come back. Uh I also should
have maybe mentioned that this question
is it's the answer is not as clean as uh
some other questions. So the the
response there was that the so for our
latest policy we actually don't have any
well we have we have maybe one data
point from that policy but most of the
buffer is not like the rest of the
buffer is not from that policy right and
so we don't actually have any really
much data at all from our current
policy. So it's not our current policy
and that's why uh this is incorrect and
in particular uh when we collect um kind
of trajectories from previous policies
uh the actions uh will be different and
that means that the next state will also
be different uh when you took that
action uh as well as the reward. Yeah.
So the policy that you're going to be
learning a value function for um I'll
phrase it slightly differently that the
policy that you'll be learning a value
function for is sort of a um some sort
of mixture of all of your past policies.
uh the
um it's it's actually like not trivial
to write it down. Like if if things were
collected in a particular way um the
policy might look something like a um
like an average over like your previous
policies um if you had n previous
policies. Now, it's actually a little
bit different than this because in some
states you might like one policy might
have kind of gone over here and another
policy might have gone over here. Uh and
so then in this state it's going to be a
mixture of policies but in this state
it's going to be uh more this policy. In
this state it's going to be a different
policy. Um so it's actually a little bit
messy. Uh but uh the thing that's
definitive is that it's not going to be
a value function for your current
policy. uh and we would like to get a
value function for our current policy uh
using data from previous policies so
that we could actually estimate this
advantage for our current policy and get
an accurate gradient for our current
policy. Um it's a little bit messy but
it's a policy that is um kind of a
conglomeration of your previous
policies. Uh and so or or some some kind
of mixture of your previous policies.
It's not something that you can very
cleanly write down. Uh but it's it's a
mixture of of your past policy.
Okay. Um the other thing that's a bit
wrong about this is that the here this
is also not the action that the policy
would have taken. And likewise when you
pass the action into the advantage
that's also not the action that the
policy would have taken. And so we'll
also see how we can fix that part. Um
but first let's talk about the value
function. And we have this key question
of how do we fit a value function for
our current policy using a replay buffer
of data from past policies.
So
one idea here is um instead of trying to
fit V uh what if we try to fit Q instead
of V.
So
um we can remember that uh Q
the Q function is very similar to the
value function uh but the it's the sum
of rewards if we start at S and take
action A. Uh so you can think of it as
uh the sum over say this is S t and a t.
Uh this is the sum of time steps
starting at t through the end of the
trajectory of the reward um r of s t
prime a t prime
um under the expectation that we're
running our policies after taking state
s and action a t and so uh this under
the expectation of pi theta conditioned
on
st.
Um so this is just the definition of the
Q function. Um the
we can now if we kind of so we have the
summation over future time steps. uh we
can actually break this um we can kind
of start to write out the summation and
in particular if we write out the first
time step uh the first time step is that
we like the first state in action is
actually just st right because that's
what we're passing into the Q function.
Uh so we can write this as we know the
reward of the first state and action
that we took and then we could have a
summation over
things starting at t + one of the sum of
future rewards.
Now for this sum of future rewards this
would now need to be an expectation
a like after sat. And so for this one,
uh, we would need, um, an expectation if
we were starting from,
uh, ST + one
under the dynamics
and,
um, and the remaining actions and end
state sampled from pi theta.
This is for pi theta.
Now this is starting to look also a lot
like a value function but for the
ST+1,
right? Uh and so you can actually also
write this in terms of Q. Uh and in
particular uh you can write this this is
equivalent to the reward at the current
time step plus um if we then kind of try
to take this one step further then we'll
have ST+1 sample by the dynamics and a
t+1 uh sampled from our policy.
Uh so if we have the expectation over
ST +1 and A+1 sampled from our policy
then the Q at the current time step is
the reward plus this expectation of the
next Q.
And so we can essentially define Q uh
recursively
like this as the reward at the current
time step plus the future Q at the next
time step. And the thing that's really
nice about this equation is that this
equation
holds for any state in action. We
haven't made any assumption about which
state in action the uh this data was
collected for.
Um and so if we walk through that on the
slides again. So we have we have data
points that are state action reward next
state. This is sampled from some other
policy and we also have the future
reward. These are this is kind of a
trajectory collected from another an old
policy. Um this action was taken from
the past policy and this future reward
depends on the past policy's actions. Um
we don't want to use the future reward
part because this this is going to
depend on the past policy actions in a
pretty complicated way.
Um but if we if we're fitting Q of SA
then we're actually passing the action
as input and it's actually okay if that
action is a bit different from what our
policy would have taken.
Um and so because that's okay um and
because we have this equation um that
that represents this recursion then we
can actually try to fit QA to a target
that looks like this.
And so we have our definition of the Q
function of the future rewards condition
on the state in action. And for any
state in action, we have this
equivalence where Q for pi theta of SA
is the reward at the current time step
plus the Q function at the next time
step where the next time you have an
expectation over the next time step and
an expectation over the next action for
a policy. Yeah, good question. So the
question was um the for this data we
have um this action and and for the Q
function um it takes this input and
action but it's still like the kind of
the rest of the trajectory was still
following a different policy right and
and we the Q needs to be like you need
to be summing the rewards for a current
policy not the other policy and the
thing that we've done here is that um if
we represent this Q uh in terms of uh Q4
our current policy
Um this actually this second term right
here is actually not using the future
data at all. uh it's it's using well
okay the the S-prime we will be using
the data uh but it's not using anything
after s prime
uh and in particular we're using our
we're using our kind of bootstrapped
estimate of Q um at the next time step
uh and the for the next action instead
of using the action that was taken in
our data we can use the action sampled
from our current policy
So we're recursively defining uh the Q
function here and the
um the only things that will maybe we
could actually just kind of go through
the next part. So what we'll do here is
we'll sample an SAS S prime from the
buffer. This A was from an old policy
but the dynamics are constant, right?
And then we'll sample an A prime from
our current policy. This is uh sample uh
from our current policy conditioned on s
prime.
And then we can estimate the q function
as the reward at the current time step
plus uh the q function for the next
state in the buffer and an action
sampled from our policy here. And
because this action is sampled from our
policy rather than uh from the data set,
then we're actually getting an estimate
uh for our current policies Q function.
So yeah, good question. So the question
was does this require that we see data
from all possible state action pairs? Uh
the there's a very good insight there.
um we don't actually need to see data
from all state action pairs, but it
means that for this target to be
accurate, we do need to have data that
covers um actions that are similar to
what our policy would be taking. Uh and
if we haven't seen that data, this Q
function is going to be uh inaccurate
and you'll need to kind of collect data
from uh from your current policy in
order to get that. Um, so this isn't
like uh we're not getting a like a
really good estimate over Q function for
free based on past policies. We still
need decent coverage of what our policy
would have done. Uh, but it means that
the um this does actually it provides
somewhat of a means to use old data. Um
and so I guess just to finish this slide
and then come back to that point uh
we'll be using uh r plus gamma x q as
our label and then we can use supervised
learning to pass as input the state and
action to a neural network and then
output try to output this label right
here. Um and again we can use kind of
the similar like L2 error between our
prediction and the target just like with
the value function. Um and to be
accurate uh the targets why these
targets need to have sufficient action
coverage and need to have uh like the
action taken from your policy can't be
wildly out of distribution otherwise
these targets will be inaccurate.
Yeah. So we'll need to have taken that
action from that state. Yeah. Um and so
if the this does make it like you need
to have um if you don't have cover like
if you don't have any data from that
state that's a problem. And then if you
have data from that state but only for
like very different actions is also a
problem. Um the some of this is also
going to be relying on like neural
networks can generalize can kind of
interpolate reasonably well and so that
helps this uh but you do need like
sufficient coverage for this to be
accurate. Yeah. So the question we
actually didn't quite get to this
equation on the board um there we have
this expectation here over the next
state and an action sample from our
policy. uh and we're going to this
equation estimates this with a single
sample where um we use we have uh ST and
A and then we're going to use the ST+1
from our data set uh which is just one
example uh to estimate this part and
then in this equation we'll use one
sample uh a t+1 um in order to estimate
this there are actually methods that you
can use kind of multiple samples to
estimate this to get um a better
estimate of this expectation. Um you
could also like as you're taking uh if
you take uh like in a batch you'll be
kind of sampling from your current
policy and so if you sample like each
data point will get a different sample.
Um so you also get um kind of multiple
samples in that way but yeah even for a
single state uh next state you could
also sample multiple actions here. Yeah.
Yeah. So we've been kind of we we
mentioned that we need sufficient action
coverage here and the question was if we
use a kale constraint or something
similar um to encourage it to stay close
to the previous policy would that be
helpful here um and the I think that
like one of the algorithms that we'll
see doesn't do that but um like in a
good idea and the uh in general we'll
see that those kinds of kale constraints
come up quite frequently in
reinforcement learning because we'll
often be assuming that we're not
deviating too far from um from our uh
from our previous policy. And yeah, it's
possible that the for the algorithm that
we'll see that could make it better in
some circumstances too.
Okay. So to walk through um okay well so
I guess what we talked about is we'll be
updating Qhat with our targets Y um
where the target is R plus um plus the Q
and critically the the state SI will be
sampled from the replay buffer but the
next action will not be from the replay
buffer. It'll be sampled from our policy
conditioned on that next state from the
buffer.
Um cool. So that'll be our revised step
three for the algorithm.
Um the last thing is what we want to do
here. So we have um instead of
estimating the value function, we
estimated the Q function. Um there's a
couple things that we'll do here for
this update.
Um the first is that it'll be convenient
to use Q instead of A. Uh, and this
means that we're not going to use a
baseline. Uh, this is going to be higher
variance, but that's going to be okay
because we're going to be using a lot
more data, like all the data from our
buffer, not just the data from our
current policy.
Uh, and then the second is that um the
current policies actions are likely
better than the past policies actions.
And so, um, for this update right here,
we'll be sampling an A from our current
policy and instead of from the action
taken in the buffer. And then uh this
will be the gradient update on our
policy uh where uh we'll be looking at
log pi of a given s times q of sa. These
a's will be sampled from our policy but
essentially using the same trick as what
we did with the q function except now
for the current state instead of the
next state.
Um so here's our full algorithm. Um
there's sort of one remaining problem
which is that the state the states in
our buffer didn't come from our current
policy. Um there isn't really anything
that we can do here. Uh but it's
actually not necessarily a bad thing. It
means that we're going to be getting a
policy on a broader state distribution
uh rather than just on the state
distribution that our policy would
visit.
Okay. Um so this is uh this is
essentially the soft actor critic
algorithm. There are other ways to
estimate this gradient um that we don't
have time to get into today but we might
go over in future lectures. There are
also some fancier ways to fit um this Q
function that we'll see in the next
lecture. Um but the the algorithm here
that that this is very very close to is
called soft factor critic or SACE. And
if we compare SACE and PO uh the more
off policy version that uses a replay
buffer is shown in orange and the less
off policy is shown in brown. And so we
see that we're able to get much more
data efficient learning um with
something like SACE than with something
that's less off policy. Um so you can be
far far more data efficient when you use
this replay buffer. Uh the downside is
that it can be a lot harder to tune
hyperparameters and generally it can be
a bit less stable um when you're using
these skew functions than compared to
PPO.
Cool. And then lastly uh when you're
fully off policy you could actually be
efficient enough to run reinforcement
learning on real robots. So in this
example um in about two hours uh the
policy learns how to uh walk forward uh
just with the algorithm that we talked
about. Uh you can also learn some kind
of cool manipulation tasks with
reinforcement learning. uh this was
seated with demonstrations is a very
precise task and you can see that
actually if you compare the performance
of this RL method it actually gets 100%
on all the tasks that they tested
whereas if you use imitation learning
you'll get a much lower success rate and
reinforcement learning is also leads to
a faster policy than um than with
imitation learning
um and then PO is a common algorithm
that's used uh if you want really stable
learning but less data efficient
learning and so if you're in simulation
for example data is not a problem. You
can collect tons and tons of data in
simulation and you can learn a policy in
simulation and then if you carefully
tune your simulator that policy might be
able to transfer to the real world. And
then there was also an example of uh in
general for manipulation sim to real
transfer is a lot harder. We're learning
how to uh do a Rubik's cube that was
trained in simulation and after about 5
minutes of this roll out uh you get a
Rubik's cube that has been completed
and that was with PO. Um PO is also a
common choice for language models. We'll
start to discuss them next week.